Um, we have the three princesses though,
remember with the crown? So, I I figured
the safest thing about Q&A is to do it
before I start talking.
So
uh some my wife reminded me other people
reminded me that we had a
question that uh the other guy said if
there's if everything's
empty then there's no for
truth and if there's no for truth
there's
no
for
four actions or four four things that
you do with the four truths. Yeah. Yeah.
And then there's no four results that
you get from the four
truths. And then there can't be
any
sa and then there's no dharma and that
means there's no Buddha and that means
there's no three jewels. That means
there's no three jewels. There's no
goodness and there's no parlance means
uh the language of the world. The normal
language of the world people can't
communicate.
And we were
gonna you guys were going to meditate on
it and tell
me why those last I mean the the the
progression of the first five six things
is clear but then it gets weird right if
there's no three jewels there's no
goodness and then there's no language of
the normal world okay so who wants to
take a shot I think hassel is
considering it. Do you want to try it?
Okay, go.
From the Pree World News Disc.
Wait, talk into the microphone. Okay.
Guess guess into the microphone.
Okay. So, my
my thoughts go into this idea
that language itself is also empty.
Words are empty. they don't have like
intrinsic meaning on themselves. So the
only way we can load them is because
they are empty and that's why we can
communicate otherwise I don't know just
the miracle that when I say water it
triggers certain mental image in others
people's mind but then because I in
Spanish let's say I can say awa and
trigger the same mental picture in other
people means like the sounds and the
word are empty the only way to for the
language to really work is because It's
empty.
Anybody else?
Thank you. I think it's good.
Why there is no
morality language? I think
it's used to
teach the dharma and then uh the 64
qualities of the Buddha's speech is the
most expensive seats then it all comes
from morality.
So if there is no morality then the
there won't be the 64 good
qualities and then the no language can
be to the
cool she cooked she and cooked us dinner
the other night I want to say it's one
of the nicest I ever had.
[Laughter]
I'll thank my mom. Yeah, please thank
your mom. She gave the recipe.
I think that there's a certain amount of
love and harmony needed in order to
agree on what a word means. So perhaps
that's the link.
If we didn't have love, we wouldn't be
able to have this connection with other
people. And I think language helps us do
that. And it's also the reason we have
some parts of the world we can't connect
with. We don't have language. We don't
have enough love perhaps.
[Applause]
I was thinking that something complex
and powerful like language must be a
huge current result of seeds of
interaction
um on helping other to
interact. But if there are no three
tools and therefore no uh causes and
effects
and therefore no morality then I just
take what I want I just live on my own
and there is no need to interact and
therefore I'm not
practicing therefore language nice
[Applause]
language connects the deceptive reality
to the ultimate reality
is there's words that are the link for
the dharma to be understood by people in
our world.
Cool.
[Applause]
Maybe one more. So yeah, kind of similar
to some of the previous answers, but
language is a is a social construct and
it takes a certain amount of
collaboration to, you know, agree on a
grammar, vocabulary. Um, and if there's
no morality, you just kill or steal to
get what you want. You don't need to
cooperate with other people. You have no
need to communicate with them.
[Applause]
Cool. I like it. Uh by the way the word
in in the native language is
uh is uh the par parlance in English
means the usual language that people use
in the normal world and
so uses this word. So I think I think
everybody's on the right track. It takes
a kind of
shared seeds, shared karma to even be
able to communicate with each other. And
when those seeds are not there, then I
think you have war and violence and
confusion. When the seats are there for
because of your goodness, as everybody
said, then then you can communicate
peacefully with each other. That's cool.
But but just to say that in the la the
last thing I'd say is
that for Arya
Nearjuna the normal reality called
talking world people in the world
talking to each other for him that's 50%
of the
reality because he says Buddha cannot
communicate higher ideas to us without
that language. So even for a Buddha they
need that
that the normal words of the world they
need it and it's necessary for Buddhas
also if it's necessary for Buddhas it
must be helpful for us okay
uh we still have about five minutes we
could do some uh other Q&A uh any kind
of Q&A is fine that's one good thing
about the gish course is they don't tell
you the debate topic when you get to the
debate
they surprise you.
Thank you.
Um in recently you mentioned a few times
about uh Maitra is closer than you think
and can you elaborate it's more and are
you based on the scripture or anything
else or how to make a connection with
Matria when he's show up in some friends
teaching and we can be there listening.
Oh good question.
I think I have to leave that one.
Okay. But my try is closer than you
think. All right. Next question.
I'm still thinking about words class
yesterday that when all the mental
afflictions and understanding is gone
what's
left and I was
thinking for example when I try to get
rid of my
anger this spot is taken up by patience
so is it even possible to get rid of the
negative ones without the positive ones
showing up right uh there's a question
like that by the way
uh there was something around your neck
that
You got it back. Okay, good. I just was
thinking there's a question like that
and um there's a question like that in
Buddhism. Are things relative? In other
words, can you have light without
darkness? You know, could you have
knowledge without ignorance? And some
people have said that dependent
origination means you cannot have light
without dark and you cannot have
enlightenment without s or like that.
And uh they say that's the meaning of
dependence. Relativity we call it
relativity is the meaning of dependence.
and and then
uh there are sections in the scripture
which uh we call in English debunk.
Debunk means they proved that that's a
silly idea that you couldn't have light
without darkness or something like that.
You could live in a in a world that
was had two sons and light all day all
the time and all night. You see what I
mean? And so they say
uh relativity is not the meaning of
dependence. You see what I mean? It's
not that you have to have evil to have
goodness in the world. You could have
goodness without evil and you would
still recognize it and you would still
experience it. Okay. So
that's that's the I I I like that. There
are sections in scripture that get into
that. They they debunk
relativity uh in favor of seeds. If you
have the seeds for it to be daylight all
day on your world, it will be daylight
all day on your world. Whether or not
there's any
darkness,
cool. We have some more time. So Ga,
here's a question from someone.
The question is about is about time and
emptiness
time. If there is not such a thing as a
partless moment of
consciousness. When we're thinking about
time, how does this relate to the law of
karma in the sense of when you plant a
seed, there's a time delay between the
planting and the ripening. And what how
can we think about that and how could it
help us?
Okay, cool.
Um, so we we did a program uh long time
ago anyway.
Um, we we in that film that they showed
from DSSEU, we had an interesting uh
class at the Institute for Advanced
Study, which is a little bit off of the
Princeton campus, and this is where
Einstein and Oenheimer went to make the
bomb.
uh they the
university sent them off the campus and
it's a kind of a
highly guarded campus and uh that's
where they developed this thing and um
it's still that way. It's still
considered kind of u kind of secret or
kind of you're not supposed to walk
around there and stuff like that. So, of
course, we went there and we walked
around. I think it was Edmund's idea and
uh we actually went to the director of
it's called Institute for Advanced and
they said, "Okay, you can have a class.
It's a beautiful day." We had decided to
have the class under a big tree and uh
out it's a perfect weather and I
remember a a fox a red fox slowly walked
through the class you know we're
like what's that about so and then uh so
that's where Einstein was the house
where he lived is nearby there we should
have gone there admin next
take some pictures. But he had this
theory that time
is relative, right? Or time time can be
time is can be curved. Space can be
curved. And I never understood it and I
never wanted to understand it. You know,
it wasn't that important to me. But I
but then I was going to teach the
emptiness of time and the emptiness of
space. I was gonna write a book called A
Better History of
Time, but the editor
of A Brief History of Time got upset at
me. But that's another story. Uh and uh
here's the idea. And and then you can
brag to people that at Diamond Mountain
you understood Einstein. Okay.
uh he said
uh if the gravity of something is very
very
heavy then it will change the path even
of light. So he he had this idea that
light was made of something that could
be affected by gravity somehow it had
mass even though not much it has some
mass. So in general when you drop a cup
uh and the mass of the earth is greater
than the mass of the cup not the size
but the mass which is almost the same
thing but if you basically if you drop a
cup the smaller thing will be attracted
to the bigger thing. So if there's light
passing from some object in the sky
coming here then that has some mass to
it. it has some substance to it. And
then if there's some real fat
thing off to the side, that light should
be attracted. It should
bend. Okay, that's easy, right? So, the
light from uh a planet, for example,
Mercury, which is the smallest planet,
it's spinning
around the closest to the sun. Since
he's so close to that fat boy called the
sun than light from Mercury that gets to
Earth, it should take a little bit
longer to get to Earth because it it's
attracted by the great gravity of the
sun. It should go in a curve, which is
what curved space means. So, so the
light coming from Mercury should take a
little bit longer to get to Einstein
predicted that
But he didn't have the tools to prove
it. They didn't have the instruments to
prove it. And then later uh they proved
it. So they waited till uh the mercury
passed behind the sun. And just when
Mercury came out from behind the sun and
they calculated the time that the light
should take to reach the earth and it
was a slight delay which means that that
part of space was curved which also
means that time is relative which means
that different people could experience
time in different ways. Okay. And that's
very much against the early Greek and
Roman and Buddhist presentations of of
science. Okay. Abid Dharma says that uh
things are made of tiny
particles and time should move at a
certain rate. Time as judged by seconds
of of the human stream of awareness
should always be the same. Everybody
should experience time the same
way. An hour for me should be the same
as an hour for you because we're living
in the same world and the hours passing
at the same speed. That's proven by the
lack of
Q&A. Uh so anyway,
uh you know that's a basic early Abid
Dharma idea. It's a basic early Greek
idea. They split time especially as
measured in the consciousness of a human
being. You know how do you experience
time and then they cut it into little
pieces called seconds and then
milliseconds and then they run out of
language. They run out of words and in
the Avid Dharma it's very cute because
they start making up words like quirks
and you know No, I'm sorry. No, that's
western science. Uh, so they call horse
particle, bull particle, chicken
particle, mouse particle, flea
particle. They give the particles names
and it's beautiful. They go down to the
10 to the 60th
power. 10 with 60 zeros after
it. And they say that's the that's the
smallest point of that's the smallest
measure of time. And if
you got
smaller then the beginning of the moment
and the end of the moment would be in
the same
place. And the same with an atom. If you
split an atom then the left left side
would touch the right side and then
there would be no atom. Okay you can
imagine it right? And then the later
Buddhist said come
on you can always split it further. you,
no matter how small a particle gets, it
still has a left side and it still has a
right side. Which means you can always
be closer to the left side and farther
away from the right side, which means
even the tiniest atom can be split. And
that's what
basically quantum physics says also that
you can keep splitting the atom and it
may lose its elemental identity, but it
you can still keep splitting. Okay? So
there is no
ultimate particle of time. There is no
set period of time. A second is is
different in each person's experience.
And an atom is different in each
person's experience. There is no base
reality. There is no fundamental measure
of time. All time is relative. Einstein
and all space is is curved. And it could
longer for things to happen to you or to
me. And I I will have a completely
different experience of of reality than
you because there's no building blocks.
There's no smallest amount of time and
there's no smallest measure of space
that exists. And then there's this thing
called what's it called?
Eisenberg's paradox. You know if the
observer moves uh the behavior of light
changes from a particle to a wave. It's
weird. Even even quantum
physicists part part of quantum physics
is that if you if the observer changes
their direction the behavior of light
and matter is different. It behaves
differently. So there is no standard
behavior of time and there is no
standard behavior of space and Buddhists
would say the guardian would say that's
because you have your own seats and I
have my own seats and time goes
different speed for me and time goes at
a different speed for you. So therefore,
end of
question, all Buddhism, the highest
schools of Buddhism, which is negative,
uh reject the idea of a smallest
particle of time and of a standard
particle of time and a standard particle
of space. They say no such thing,
impossible. Okay? Which means that each
person's experience is objective and and
time will the time spent listening to
Gisha could go very slow for some people
and they're like when's he gonna
finish? Okay. Got it. Cool. All right.
Let's get to uh we got to go on to our
next class. Okay. Ready? And I'll take
I'll do some more questions. Uh, so
here's what happened. Chapter 26, can I
say? Am I right?
Yeah. Chapter 26 is an investigation of
the 12 links of the wheel of life. Okay.
And
uh here you got to understand
historically what's going on. uh Lord
Buddha gave a talk called the 12 links
of the wheel of life. Okay. Uh he gave a
famous famous talk about the 12 things.
It's short. It's like two pages. Uh
and he gave that talk and then uh it's
kind of beautiful
uh on on three different occasions that
I found in the sutras.
Uh Buddha had a reason why he couldn't
give a lecture to someone directly and
there weren't any tape
recorders. Uh
so he by the and and the the one that I
like the most is a princess in Sri
Lanka which is far far to the south of
India. Right. So the gardener was
probably living in a place called
Atala uh in south India near not far
from Mysore India and then
uh he was sorry Nagarajer
uh Buddha was up in North India near
Vonasi and
Raja and then uh there was a queen in
Sri Lanka and uh there was a lot of
trade going on there was similar to the
Silk Road. So there was a trade route
between Sri Lanka and and India very
very common to go across and she uh met
some merchants from Baronasi or North
India who knew Lord Buddha and uh they
told her about Buddha and this queen due
to a past life she's called the lady of
pearls by the way and she had a past
life experience with the Buddha
And then he sends her the after
listening to the merchants, he sends her
a painting. He puts the 12 links into a
painting and he he wants to communicate
with her. It's a tape recording. Got it?
Of his teaching because he can't send a
tape recording. And uh so he sent a a
painting and that was the 12 links of
the of the wheel of life. So in his
penultimate chapter in the next and last
chapter which must be a place of great
importance
uh he covers the 12 links and we have a
12 links master it's the mayor of
uh Sugang finished a book a very
important and very difficult book about
the 12 links and it's
in
infinitable editing right now it's being
edited
Uh, don't say three years. It pains me.
Uh, anyway, it's coming out very soon.
And, uh, it's done. The book is done. We
just haven't put it out yet. And I'll
probably just force it out. Okay. Like,
what do you call
that? In the hospital C-section. I'm
going to do a Gishi Michael C-section.
Um so anyway
uh he's translated one book and then he
started on a second book uh that was
written 1 1700 years ago by master busu
which is an explanation of the Buddha's
teaching on the 12 things. Okay. Now
tonight today we have this I I'm going
to do two classes on chapter 26.
Yeah. And uh it's an explanation of the
12 links, but I want you to get a
feeling
historically what's going on. And I
think Sugan will appreciate it more than
anybody. We are
struggling through an explanation of the
12 lings by
Basandu that we discovered in all
project. Okay. and there's no commentary
and there's no oral tradition and the
manuscript is
probably very messed up and it was
translated by a guy who was drunk I
think so and that's all we have we have
no other we have no other tools so me
and Sug gang are like yeah let's try
because no one has touched that book in
2 years 17 centuries okay so we're
working order and we're doing okay. I
I'd say we're struggling but we're
making it. We're going to make it. Uh
now the cool thing here is we have
somebody a hundred years before
that. Okay. And that's that's the cool
thing for us today is that uh we have
someone who's 150 years before busy. So
he's got the raw teaching on the 12
links. He's got the raw teaching of the
wheel of life. And then what's his take
on the 12 links? Because this is the
first take of any Mahayana teacher of
any bodhis sappa teacher. This is the
first bodhisappa to explain the 12
links. Okay. And I I started reading it
and I was like, "Oh man, I don't know
how I'm going to make a class out of
this. It's 12 verses. Everything else is
like security would take 300 verses. The
Guardian has got 12 verses on the 12
links and he doesn't even use all of
them. Uh so I'm like I don't know if
this is going to work out. And then I
read it and I was like flooring. I was
like astounded and it's unbelievable and
it's an understanding of the 12 links
that I have never seen after that. So
I'm like wow you know. So I thought uh I
got inspired and I stayed up almost all
night couldn't do other people's
work. All right? So you
understand and uh I
translated the verses. Okay. So uh I'd
like to teach them to you that way.
Okay. And uh and we'll we'll start.
Okay. Okay. And it will take more than
one. We'll take it'll run into the next
I think.
Yeah. Okay. So, by the
way, we did a book with my teacher
uh 45 years ago of the wheel of life and
uh we uh I had a print in my possession
uh that was done somewhere in the
Himalayas and I bought it from a guy
that walked out of the Himalayas and I
was 23 years old and Uh, I gave it to my
stepmother and she passed away and she
gave it back to me and I have it so it's
cool. And anyway, uh, it had it's a very
fine Wheel of Life print. And so what I
did was I took the pictures of the Wheel
of Life off that print, which I think is
the best print I've ever seen, and I
gave them to you. Okay, here we go. Uh
26.1. Next
one. Yeah. Okay. And uh I'll give you
the images or something, but here's
we're going to start the 12 verses of
our inagonous presentation of the wheel
of life and it's unique and it's special
and it's amazing. Okay. And I added
the drawings. Okay. Uh they were cleaned
up by a lady from
Guadalajara who's a
genius graphics designer and a super
kind person and just serves people all
day long. Her name is
[Music]
[Applause]
Gina and and years ago she she she
cleaned it up for me and then uh I had
some I wanted to it adjusted then I
asked Rosa Fria and she she did some
more adjustments. So the the drawings
are pretty good. Okay. So, uh, anyway,
that's the first two links of the wheel
of life. That's why they kind of curved
like that. You got to imagine the left
hand one on top of the right hand one.
And uh, what's the image for
misunderstanding? Yeah. A blind a blind
person. And the stick is supposed to
indicate that the person is blind.
That would mean not understanding
that a bad driver that you run into on
the road from Phoenix to
Tucson is coming from
you. And if you get upset at them, you
just created 10 more bad drivers. Okay,
that's a kind of
blindness, right? So that's the
blindness. By the way, that's my one of
my remaining bad habits is
to I have an AI problem with other
drivers if you know what I'm talking
about. Anyway, something happens to my
fingers. Uh and then uh second picture
is by the way Suken confirmed it. People
love that when they when their
self-existent perception is confirmed by
another person. So when Suden and
Shinten bought their new car and they
drove it and and Sugang said now I
understand about Arizona drivers. I said
I told you. Okay. So there's
misunderstanding. What's the second
picture on the
right? Yeah. Making fresh karma. Making
fresh karma. Fresh karma.
Okay. Uh here's here's Arya Nagarajuna
opening comments on the 12 links to him
it's important enough to put at the end
of his book of his most important book.
Okay. And he says blinded by
misunderstanding we collect together the
three kinds of fresh karma. And this is
the karma that makes us go where it is
we go which is gutting gachi in the
sanskrit. It sounds cool in the
sensei that's why you go where you go.
Okay. And so he that's okay. This part's
okay, right? We don't understand what's
going on. Uh what's the three kinds of
fresh
karma? Easy.
Good karma, bad karma, neutral
karma. The only one that's kind of hard
to understand is is neutral is
the most of the karma we do is neutral.
And so that that creates the background
world like the dirt outside. You don't
stop I mean my wife does and say how
beautiful the stones
are. When we first built Diamond
Mountain, my teacher was still alive.
Everybody used to pick up heart-shaped
stones and take them back to New Jersey.
And then finally, my teacher said, "No
more heart-shaped stones from Diamond
Mountain." I understand there's
heart-shaped stones there, but I don't
want them piled up in my
house.
So, that's neutral karma. Okay? It just
makes the the background stuff. Okay?
And So there is a a lot of neutral karma
going on. We just don't appreciate it.
Okay? There's nothing that's not made by
karma. Even stuff that you don't feel
good about or you don't feel bad about
or you don't even notice is still made
by karma. Okay? So that's okay. This
part uh by the way where you go in in
Sanskrit and in and in Tibetan means
your next life. Okay? When they say go
where you go, it means your next life.
It could also mean, you know, whether or
not breakfast is going to be tasty,
which is a big concern of mine. But, uh,
normally when you see gachami or gacha,
gati, it means birth, rebirth, where you
go in your rebirth. So, that's okay.
And by the way, I think Sugang and me
both. I I don't know about you, Sugen,
but me personally, it's kind of
disturbing to me that the wheel is not
in
order, you know, if you really
understand the wheel, it goes
like, you know, it's it should have
been, you know, and it's it's not
really. And why does it jump around? And
can the gardener help us understand why
it jumps around? That would be sweet.
Okay. So, let's see if he does. Okay.
So, first
verse, you're okay, right? Everything's
kind of easy. The Sanskrit, it it reads
quite sweetly. By the way, uh if you are
interested to learn
Sanskrit, memorize this book. Okay? If
you're interested in Sanskrit, memorize
this book. He writes perfect Sanskrit
and he writes it in a simple simple way.
He's the he believes in the simplest
words are the most powerful words. The
garjuna is is the simplest writer in
Buddhism and the deepest. Okay, he uses
simple words in a deep way. If you want
to memorize
Sanskrit, if you want to learn Sanskrit,
learn these verses. The nice thing is
it's in it's in meter. Okay? So it's
easy to memorize.
eight and it's all like that. Why did
they write it in eights and eights and
eights? Because if you forget something,
it turns out six or four. Okay? And then
you know you forgot something. Got it?
If the beats don't work
out. So if you're And by the way, uh
Christina Cassico, where are you? She's
teaching a Sanskrit course uh that goes
on at the same it goes it flows all year
like the mix nuts like the Shenzong
Tower class. If you're interested in
Sanskrit you can learn from her. I don't
emphasize Sanskrit myself
because 99% of Sanskrit was destroyed.
So out of the 4,600 books from India
which survive
uh they only survive in Tibetan. They
don't survive in Sanskr there's only a
few. Uh this is one of them by the way
but uh you know if you're going to spend
the time to learn a foreign language I
would suggest to them because you got
300,000 books in Sanskrit. you have
maybe a hundred that survive and it's
not enough to really master it. You see
what I mean?
So, it's good to know it in case you run
into a problem. You can check the
sensor. In this book,
uh in this book, uh the people in the
last 20 centuries have mixed up Ming and
Mick.
uh I and name
uh and then there's a very common
expression
mukar name and form which is the fourth
right fourth link and someone wrote
muk which means I and form instead of
muk okay and uh I corrected it and then
I checked the Sanskrit and the muk was
correct
the mistake was correct. Okay. So, if
you have the Sanskrit, you can avoid
fixing something that's not
broken. You avoid changing the
guard, which is helpful. Okay. Anyway,
that part's easy. Let's go to the next
verse. 26 point Oh, sorry. 26.2, right?
Okay. Triggered by fresh karma.
Consciousness makes beings make their
hindrance. Okay. And by the way, if you
think I'm just being repetitive with the
makes and the makes or something like
that, he does it. He's cute. He likes to
be cute. He says we go on our goings and
we make our makes. Okay. I didn't invent
it. And then he says, so consciousness
makes us make our entrance. Once
consciousness is settled then name and
form are formed. Then he he's making
another pun
right he's making another pun.
So triggered by fresh
karma. So that that's kind of a problem
again that
uh the link between second link and
third link is not that clear because you
think you should go through link number
8 9 sorry 9 10 and
11. It it should go to 9 10 11
three right rebirth uh strong desire
weaker
desire but
This is how Nearjuna who's the first
great commentator on the 12 links in
history. He says no problem. Link number
two goes to link number three easily.
You don't have to go jump to link number
eight n 10. Okay. So it's cool if you're
a wheel of life specialist
like you you're like ah finally
someone's following the wheel around in
the in the real order. Okay. All right.
So, triggered by fresh karma,
consciousness makes beings make
ignorance. So, what's so the first link
is misunderstanding. We're not going to
say ignorance anymore because it is a
false understanding.
Misunderstanding. And then that causes
you
to make
karma fresh. Well, let's say karma. And
then that causes you to have a mind
that's headed towards your next birth.
That makes sense. That if you explain
the 12 links this way, it makes sense.
You know that the wheel is moving in a
wheel. And we haven't seen that really.
That's his version, which fits the
order. Then what happens next? And by
the way, you got the picture here. the
two guys in the Yeah. On the left you
have the monkey entering the house.
Okay. And and that's the that's your
mind entering the womb of your mother.
Okay. The monkey entering the house is
your mind pushed by your
karma across
death. By the way, when you get to my
age, you start thinking about it. Okay?
And it's nice that you have a teacher
who's planting it in your mind when
you're so young because you'll need it
later. You'll be curious later. When it
gets closer, you'll be saying, "What?
How does that work again?" Because I
might have to go through that next week.
Okay. So, here it is. Uh, your mind
survives death and then your mind looks
for a new place. That's the monkey
looking to the window. Okay. And then on
the right you have
what? Yeah. You have body and mind. It's
called namarupa name and form but it
means body and
mind. And and there's two guys in a
boat. Okay. And that repres then he says
uh once consciousness is settled and you
never see that language used in our
commentaries and it's so cool. Once
consciousness is settled
where? In the womb. Yeah. Okay.
uh beings make their entrance into
the mom into the womb. Okay? And then
once they get settled there, once the
monkey gets settled, he develops into he
or she develops into a body and a mind
in the womb.
Okay? It's called
piece of spit and then piece of gooey
spit and then piece of sticky gooey
spit. And these are the stages of
gestation in the
um so that's cool. That's maybe the
first time we've seen the wheel go in
the right order and it's a plausible
explanation so far. What he's going to
do when he gets to it later, I
don't. So already to
me it's helping my understanding of the
original real life and it makes more
sense. We have never had anyone explain
it this way and he tends to do that. The
guardian tends to do
that with many topics. He he gives the
earliest and the best
explanation. All right let's go to the
next verse.
[Music]
Yeah. Once name and form have formed,
you see how he's
playing? Once name and form have formed,
the six doors of sense make their
arrival. And based on the six doors of
sense, contact makes its perfect
appearance. The guardian never uses an
extra word without great meaning.
Why he says perfect
appearance? By the
way, the history of Buddhism is trying
to figure out
nar. Okay. And and there are hundreds of
there are thousands of books to explain
his emptiness teachings.
Okay? But he well he wrote common he
didn't write formal comment text. He
wrote poetry. What I'm trying to say is
this is all you get. You got to figure
it out. Okay? And and I think he
intended it that way. I think he wanted
I think he's giving you clues and he
says you figure it out.
Columbbo, you know, the older people
understand. Uh my llama had an addiction
to Columbbo. It's a murder mystery
detective guy. that every week for like
10 years. He solved a different murder.
Okay. All right. Uh here's the pictures.
All right. Check out the pictures at the
top. Uh on the left is which number is
again? Number five. Yeah, number five is
six. That's how you can remember it.
Number five is the six doors of sense.
Okay. And the heart center gives them
[Music]
Woo. Okay. Eye, ear. It goes down. I,
ear, nose, tongue, skin, and mind. Okay.
So, those are the six doors of sense.
They're pictured as empty
windows. Okay. They're pictured as
buildings with empty windows. It's the
senses developing in the womb. It's the
child's
sense organs, the
eyes. Why didn't it come before body and
mind? They take time. Yeah, it takes
time to develop. The eye the eyes are
not fully developed, I guess, till you
come out.
So there's empty houses, which means
uh there's a window, but there's nobody
looking out the window yet. Okay? And
there's nothing they're looking at yet.
Your sense organs are developing. And in
Buddhism, we include
the thought as the sixth
sense. In the in English, we we normally
don't include the thought as a sense as
a sense. In Buddhism we say six senses.
All
[Music]
right. Now
uh then the monkey comes to the
window. Okay. The monkeyy's inside the
house. The monkey the mind goes to the
window. For the first time the eyeball
is formed. The eye is working. Then the
mind you can picture the mind in the
skull behind the eye. And then for the
first time the monkey looks out the two
windows and makes contact with the
outside world. Okay. And uh that's
called what's the picture? It's the
contact of a man and a woman in
bed. And it it's it's meant to
symbolize the monkey looking out the
window and making contact with things
that they see. You see? It's cool,
right? And and so to make it intimate
and to make it strong uh Lord Buddha
used the image of two of a man and and
his wife in bed that they are touch
making contact with each other. But what
it means is the monkey of your mind is
looking out the window of your eyeball
and making contact with colors and
shapes for the first time. You know the
baby opens their eyes and then they see
And that's called contact. And for
Near, it's crucial moment. It's a big
moment. He says
what? Perfect appearance. He And by the
way, he uses perfect uh three times in
the verse in the Sanskrit,
right? Christina, he says,
So he's he's he's he's emphasizing
perfect per
perfect. What's it
mean? Now now you got to with
nega you can read 18 commentaries on it
but what do you guys think it means? Why
why is the
contact perfect?
relate to birth coming out of the womb.
So really uh you your your school by the
way this is how all the school started
with neg basically and uh so her school
is some kind of mind only variant says
uh when I made contact with the outside
world this is perfect something full
full experience of
karma anybody
I don't
know somehow for Arya Naraja the contact
is crucial
I think that maybe the observer appears
at this point say the observer appears
at this at this point so someone was
observing okay first contact with the
outside world first observation of the
I would guess that the world that the
monkey experience is perfect. The
illusion is so real. The effect of
reality is very real and perfect. Yeah,
it seems we can almost say that's the
first quote reality because it's so
concrete. You know, you're seeing
colors. You're smelling smelling.
Smelling smells. One more guess and then
I'm going to read you the next verse,
which proves you're all wrong.
It's the moment before the mind starts
to discriminate. Therefore, perfect.
That's okay. I That's a little tricky.
Okay, let's go on. Let's go on. We're
going to go on. Uh, by the
way, this was too ambitious to teach you
all the verses of this chapter. That
would take a
whole This course was supposed to take
six months. This is year number seven.
Okay. So, we got to get moving. All
right. 26.4 is next. Can I say
Yeah. And by the way, here's something
sug
uh we don't have.
Right. And by the way, there's no
picture. He hasn't gone on to another
link yet. He's making a comment about
the first contact with the outside
world. And he says, "You can only have
contact with the outside world if there
is instrument of perception, the eye. If
there is something to see, the colors or
the shapes, your mom. Okay. And if
there's what draws them
together, which uh Chon Lama says yila,
which means
attention, shifting attention. You know,
you shift your attention to what you
see. At some point the the baby when
they come out and open their eyeball
then you can imagine their mind shifts
to the window. Their mind swings to the
window and looks out the window. Okay.
And he calls it what draws them
together. It could have a deeper
interpretation. What draws the mind to
that particular
object? Karma. Why did you meet the I
mean the irritating person?
Okay, got it. So I think I think when he
says what draws them together, he's
being cute, which is very
negative. You know, he like loves to
drop hints
and be funny and wear weird hat, stuff
like that.
Okay. All right. Uh what draws them
together? Thus it is that consciousness
arises dependent upon name and form.
Sukang should be
irritated. Why?
Okay. Yeah. Now he's gone. One, two,
three, four,
three. Okay. It should be irritating.
I'll say it again.
He's saying once you look out the
window and your eyes open for the first
time and you make contact with objects,
then you can be
aware. But awareness came before that.
Awareness is the monkey that was looking
to get to get into the mom's womb. We
had awareness already in the garden. Why
are you going backwards?
Yeah, I think by by definition it's a
different consciousness. This is a sense
consciousness. The other one is your
mind in general entering your mom's.
That is a big
difference. Your mind as it perceives
the outside world and your mind as it
enters your mom nine months before that.
Yeah. Sugang says they're not talking
about the same consciousness. This
conscious is not the same one that's
link number three. Okay. Good. Okay. Uh
I didn't put a picture because I agree.
Okay. Understand? Okay. All right. Next
verse. Luckily, my wife had a long phone
call last night. She helps
people. Then I get to work.
Okay. All
[Music]
right. Now, let's look at the picture.
What's the picture
here? Yeah, it's the grossest picture in
history. We went to Singapore airport
one time. To to land in Singapore is so
amazing.
uh at least from some gates to get to
the baggage area you have to walk
through the butterfly
zoo, right? Is it still
there
park? Yeah. You go into a special you go
through a special area where it's all
very kind of humid and lots of orchids,
which is the definition of
simore. And then there's uh they keep a
butterfly museum a butterfly zoo
butterfly park and they're flying all
around you as you're trying to figure
out which baggage belt your stuff is on.
And it's kind of cool. Okay. Uh
so here he's got
um first person uh having feelings after
contact. Okay. Contact leads to feeling.
All right. What was the
contact out with the outside world?
Okay. You have your first contact and
immediately that creates an impression.
Oh, that's pretty or that's ugly or I
don't care about that. Either way, okay,
you you start to have the three kinds of
feeling right away. He says that coming
together of the three of eye and form
and consciousness meaning the eye and
the colors and shapes and the awareness
that's contact that was the man and the
lady touching each other which is the
most primitive primordial kind of
contact and then that contact of the
mind and the outside world leads to
feelings. Okay. And
Are you a guardian? I add when he adds
words pay
attention. Okay. So he added
all when he got to feelings he added
all. Why do you think he added all?
Anybody have opinion? He didn't say he
did not say you make contact with the
outside world you you get feelings. He
said you make contact with the outside
world you get all your feelings.
Why did he
add some?
Maybe because
um there's no other way that feelings
occur or it's negative and positive and
neutral. It's all Oh, so they all have
to occur that way, I think. So, anybody
else? Somebody's either she has to go to
the bathroom or she wants to
Maybe because there were already
feelings when the child is in a womb, it
already has feelings and when it's opens
the eyes, then really all feelings are
there. Yeah. Like not just inside
feelings, outside feelings about outside
things. Nice. That's cool.
By the way, you're all still wrong as
usual.
Anybody else want to be wrong? Stanley
likes to be wrong.
I think it's he's referring all three
kinds of feelings, good, bad, and
neutral. Yeah, that's possible.
Behind you when you
maybe because the child when it sees the
outside world, it sees it coming from
its own side and that misunderstanding
triggles triggers other feelings. That's
a very sexy
nar
idea. If if he wasn't thinking of that,
he should have been.
Okay. Uh let's go to the next verse. See
if it clears up the
mystery. And we are on a time frame
here. And you're going to go
into
retreat for three days, right?
Wednesday, Thursday, two and a half. So
we kind of got to get keep this. I gotta
finish it. How long?
with or without Q&A. Without Q&A. We did
Q&A. Okay. All right. Let's rush on to
this next
pictures.
[Music]
Um then we got what we call the I call
it the two desires. Uh initial desire
and strong desire. Okay. They make two
different links of the wheel of life
with desire. Okay, they're starting to
want something and then they're strongly
wanting something. Initial desire and
then strong desire. Initial desire and
then strong desire. Eight and nine,
right? Link eight and link nine. What's
seven? Feeling. What's
six? Country was five doors of Okay,
good. Uh here's his commentary. Feelings
are the trigle trigger for initial
desire. Initial desire is meant for
those things that we feel. And once we
have initial desire, there comes
advanced desire in the four forms of
this desire. Okay. So
uh the the important part of this verse
is the first part. Okay.
And uh what was the question last time
about feelings? All the feelings. Yeah.
And now now in my opinion, what he's
saying is uh what keeps the wheel moving
at this point is that you have those
feelings. You see what I mean?
Um the his definition of desire is you
have desire for the things you feel. You
see what I mean? You have to feel first
and then you want it. Okay? You have to
taste candy first before you get
addicted to candy.
and and that's his he wants to draw a
strong connection between link number
seven and link number eight and nine.
Okay. So gang, why is link number eight
and nine so
crucial in the
wheel? Why is desire so crucial?
They are almost at the same place at the
misunderstanding as the first link that
will cause the wheel to turn self. At at
link number two, you plant karma. And I
always give the example of my wife
teaching me to plant watermelon
seeds. You know, she's like, "Let's go
gardening." She said, "Do you know where
watermelons come from?" This has been 10
years ago. She said, "Do you know where
watermelons come from?" I said, "Yeah."
She said, "Where?" I said, "From the
back of the store." They're somehow they
grow them in the back of the store and
they bring I always see them come out
the door with the watermelons. There
must be something back there making
watermelons. She's like, "No, they grow
on these vines and you have to plant
them." Then it was secured. I don't know
if you remember, we had a bag of seeds,
which is ridiculous because every
watermelon has 10,000 seeds in it. Then
you buy a bag of seeds, you know, they
give you 12 seeds for $6 or something.
So I'm like, buy the seeds and then I
said, "Well, how do you plant them?" She
says,
"Duh. Lick your thumb. Stick it in the
ground." Okay, what next? Put the seed
in the hole. Okay. What next? Cover it.
Then what next? That's all. Then I sat
there and I was sitting there and she
said, "What are you doing?" And I said,
"I'm waiting." And she's like, "You're
gonna wait till October. This is
April." She's like, "They don't come
out, you know." And and I always I'm
fascinated by the idea that for some
reason when you put the seed in the
ground and then you get it wet, it's the
factory opens. All the workers wake up.
All the machines
start and they're all running around
saying, "Let's push a sprout out. Let's
push a sprout out." You know, somehow
they're all sleeping in the package and
then when you the water touches it and
the sunlight and the ground and then
suddenly they all wake up and they start
we got to get this sprout out. We got to
get this sprout out and then the sprout
comes out. So anyway, link number
three,
sorry,
two. Link number two is the watermelon
seed in April when you push it under the
ground. And that's called can I say
sunscara? Sunscar. Yeah. And then uh
when it gets wet, when it gets
warm, when the time has
passed, then the sprouts ready to come
out. That's what link
10. That's link number 10.
Ripe curve. Ripe curve. So try to
imagine the difference of a watermelon
seed between the April and October, you
know, or April and June or so. You put
the seed under the ground, it's just
sitting there. It's not doing anything.
Then somehow the water wakes up all the
workers and then somehow they run around
and then it's ready to burst out with a
sprout later. Okay? Something happens
inside the seed. I think it's
fascinating.
Somebody woke up in the goddamn thing
and they're running around going, "We
got to get this bread out. We got to get
this sprout out." You know, something
has changed inside. So Buddhism
distinguishes between the seed in the
package or the seed when you first stick
it under the ground and then they
distinguish between that and the seed at
the moment that it's ready to produce a
sprout. What makes it ready to produce a
sprout is number eight and nine, the two
kinds of desire desire. And but but what
Negardian is saying here, which to me is
very exciting, you know, he's
saying it's the feelings that create the
desire because you want to feel
good. Human beings want what makes them
feel good. So what opens the karmas in
your
mind is you want to feel good. So, he's
big on the connection between seven and
eight. He's big. He's very big on it,
you know, like, wow, how do you go from
feelings to desire? Duh. Feelings is
what you desire. Got it? Okay. He's very
big on that. He he wants you to focus on
that. Your karmas can't open if you
don't have mistaken desire.
And and th those that desire cannot come
unless you can feel things. And that
cannot come unless you can contact the
outside world. And that cannot come
until your sense organs have formed. And
that cannot come until you enter the
room. And that cannot come until your
mind moves through through the B. Okay.
Got it. Cool. Cool. All right. What's
the four forms of desire? I forget.
I'm sure Tony Lama Tony Llama said it by
the way. Let me
see. Well, I'll give it to you next
time.
Okay. Uh that's why you have Chony Lama.
Yeah. Anyway, I think it's similar to
the four negative emotions in book
yesterday which are supposed to be
residents in the messed up consciousness
number seven. Okay. And here's the list
that Chony Lama gives if you're
interested. Uh regular
desire philosophical
views is difficult.
What was the third one in
words? Was it
pray? Not sure. Anyway, Chi Lama says
staying in the place. It could be a
carving mistake. And then the fourth one
is uh believing the inner
self. So anyway, those are the four they
can start.
[Music]
What verse are we
on? What's the next
verse? Number
seven. Uh, he's kind of he's not
far
26.7, right? Am I right? Okay, good.
Yeah. There's no picture here. When
there is advanced desire, the existence
of the one who desires will
flower. When there is no advanced
desire, we are liberated and then no
suffering life will come. It's kind of a
description of
the kind of a description
of if you have link number 10, right?
Okay. Advanced desire. No, nine. If you
have link number
nine, then 10 will come.
Existence will
flower. If you can stop your desire,
which is seeing things as not coming
from you, which allows you to get
irritated. Okay? As long as you remember
this person's coming from
you, you will
avoid perpetuating them. Okay. As long
as you understand a person is an
irritating person is coming from you,
you will stay cool because you don't
like them. Okay. The way the way a
Buddhist fights with another person is
to not cause them to come
back, which is what really usual
fighting does. Got it? How do you fight
an irritating person
in just be happy?
Okay. All right. How do you make them
come back again? Yeah. Get in. Okay. All
right. Good. Uh so where there is no
link number nine, there's no rebirth and
there's no suffering left. We are
liberated. So he takes this
point between eight between nine and 10.
He takes that as as liberation. When we
talk about the wheel of life, we try to
talk about a place where you can break
it. Okay? When we talk about the wheel
of life, we try to talk about a weak
point where you can attack it. And by
the way, I I had this question since two
days ago. I was going to ask Master
C. If I tell you that in this class
which finishes in 30
seconds. Uh we don't have time to finish
all 12 verses
here. Um if he's already up to
rebirth, let's say he's already up to
link number 12, but he's not done with
his 12
verses. as as master
sane wheel of life experts. You probably
got your own house called Wheel of Life
house. Uh and you're the master of it.
Uh what's he going to spend the rest of
the verses
on? Like if he if he if he's got 12
verses total by verse eight he's covered
the 12 lavs. What else is there to do? I
think we'll focus on
for example like a feelings for example
about why is because in order to stop
all this looks like I'll give you the
Tibetan
oh how to how they trigger and how we
stop the trigger yeah yeah when you
teach the wheel of life you
traditionally teach it how you get into
trouble and then you teach how to how to
turn it back on it okay so the rest of
the verses
basically how to get it to turn itself
back. I I didn't have time in this class
to cover, you know, rebirth is easy.
Gashi,
old hm dying, getting old and dying.
Those are easy. Okay, those are I mean
we'll cover them, but and then he and
then then wisely he tells you how to
turn the wheel back, how to how to shut
down the wheel. And that's the rest of
the verses and we will cover them. I
want to go through all of them. Then I
thought I would make a nice appendix in
your next book. Okay. Yeah. I don't
think anyone has translated this, but
it's kind of cool or no one's really
gone deep into it. I think I had one
more thing. What was that?
Yeah, he's gonna talk
about what's that? Oh, that's the what's
the classic question, Master Sugang,
about the 12th link? What's the classic
question that new people ask about the
wheel of life?
How how does the name of the link is
gashi which means oh why
why old age and death are in the same
link instead of different links. Yeah.
The 12th link is called getting old and
dying. And there's many many questions
for 2,000 years. Why the heck aren't
there 13 weeks?
Why did he
stuff two things into the 12th ring?
That's the classic question. Any
opinion? Cat has an answer. I'm sure
it's correct.
Maybe because we do not necessarily get
old before dying. Nice. That's the
classic answer.
That's a $100 answer to a Z
question.
Okay. Uh Lord Buddha purposely put
getting old and dying in one link so
that you would ask the question, how
come he stuffed two things into one
wing? And the answer to the quiz is some
people die in the womb.
We don't know. And then that's supposed
to make you
appreciate that people die out of
order. Sometimes the old Buddhist
teacher keeps living
longer and the young student who was
concerned about their last surgery dies
in a car accident on the way to the
airport.
Understand? So we all have to imagine
that we could die at any moment. Doesn't
matter your age or doesn't matter if
you're healthy or not, your life is
going well or not. You can die
anytime. Therefore, he stuffed the last
two into the 12th minute.
Okay. Some people don't get some many
people don't get the opportunity to get
old before they die. Cool. Not cool. But
we we're stopping it, right? We're
stopping the wheel of life. Okay. why he
put it here at the end of his book, what
what he's going to say about it. I think
that's worth thinking about in your
retreat. Okay. So, this I'm trying to
give you things to think about in your
retreat other than what's for dinner,
which is always a favorite retreat
meditation. And good luck in your
retreat.
And it's it's my experience in retreat
that uh if you're gonna get distracted
uh get distracted about people you know
who are sick or people who are are
having personal problems with their
marriage or something like that. You
know that you you
you can never waste your time in retreat
if you're
distracted to thinking about by helping
other people. That's that's never a
distraction. Okay? So, if you're having
trouble with distraction, go to that
distraction. Okay? Start thinking about
people you know who need who need you
and and start uh thinking about them and
then that's never a distraction. Okay,
cool. Have a nice retreat. See you
later.